<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="devel">
	<title>Building, Packaging, and Contributing to adcli</title>

	<section id="devel-links">
		<title>Helpful Resources</title>

		<para>Use the following to find more information about
		contributing to adcli beyond what's in this manual:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.freedesktop.org/software/realmd/adcli/">Website</ulink></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><ulink url="mail:authentication@lists.freedesktop.org">Mailing list</ulink></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><ulink url="https://bugs.freedesktop.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=realmd&amp;component=adcli">Bugzilla</ulink></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>

	<section id="devel-building">
		<title>Compiling adcli from Source</title>
		<para>This describes how to compiling the adcli package from
		source code. This is normally only necessary for those wishing to
		contribute to the project or package adcli.</para>

		<para>You can download
		<ulink url="http://www.freedesktop.org/software/realmd/releases/">tarballs
		of the releases</ulink> of adcli or
		<ulink url="http://cgit.freedesktop.org/realmd/adcli/">check
		out the source code from git</ulink>. This documentation will not
		go into all the details of how to get your development environment
		set up and instead focus on the what's unique to compiling adcli.</para>

		<section id="devel-building-dependencies">
			<title>Dependencies</title>

			<para>Besides the default autotools, binutils and GCC, adcli requires the
			following development dependencies to build:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>OpenLDAP client libraries</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>MIT Kerberos libraries</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>On <emphasis role="strong">Debian</emphasis> or <emphasis role="strong">Ubuntu</emphasis> you can use the following command to
			install the dependencies:</para>

<programlisting>
$ sudo apt-get install build-essential autoconf automake xmlto xsltproc \
         libkrb5-dev libldap2-dev libsasl2-dev
</programlisting>

			<para>On <emphasis role="strong">Fedora</emphasis> you can use the following command to install the
			dependencies:</para>

<programlisting>
$ sudo yum groupinstall "Development Tools"
$ sudo yum install automake autoconf xmlto xsltproc krb5-devel openldap-devel \
    cyrus-sasl-devel
</programlisting>

		</section>

		<section id="devel-building-unix">
			<title>Building on UNIX</title>
			<para>adcli uses the standard GNU build system, using autoconf for package
			configuration and resolving portability issues, automake for building makefiles
			that comply with the GNU Coding Standards, and libtool for building shared
			libraries on multiple platforms. The normal sequence for compiling and
			installing adcli is thus:</para>

<programlisting>
$ ./configure --prefix=/usr --sysconfdir=/etc...
$ make
$ make install
</programlisting>

			<para>If you've checked out the source code from git, then the
			<command>configure</command> script does not yet exist. So use
			the following instead:</para>

<programlisting>
$ ./autogen.sh --prefix=/usr --sysconfdir=/etc ...
$ make
$ make install
</programlisting>

			<para>The standard options provided by GNU autoconf may be passed to the configure
			script. Please see the autoconf documentation or run <literal>./configure --help</literal>
			for information about the standard options. In particular you probably want to adjust
			the <literal>--prefix=/xxx</literal> argument depending on your system and development
			environment.</para>

			<para>Make sure that the <literal>--sysconfdir=/etc</literal> matches the directory
			where the the MIT kerberos library stores its <literal>krb5.conf</literal>. This is
			usually <literal>/etc</literal></para>
		</section>

		<section id="devel-building-configure">
			<title>Extra Configuration Options</title>

			<para>In addition to the normal options, the configure script in the adcli
			supports these additional arguments:</para>

			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><option>--disable-debug</option>, <option>--enable-debug</option></term>
					<listitem><para>By default adcli is built with debug symbols assertions and
					and precondition checks. Enabling the debug option configures even more
					detailed debug build, including disabling optimization. Disabling the debug
					option is not recommended, as it disables all assertions, preconditions and
					internal consistency checks, although it may result it a slightly faster
					library.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><option>--disable-doc</option></term>
					<listitem><para>Disables building of the documentation and command line manual.
					The documentation is built in the <literal>doc/html/</literal> directory of
					the build.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><option>--enable-strict</option></term>
					<listitem><para>Enables strict checks during building of adcli. All
					compiler warnings become errors.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			<para></para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="devel-building-style">
		<title>Coding Style</title>

		<para>We use a code style similar to the linux kernel. Use tabs
		to indent and spaces to align/wrap beyond the indentation level.</para>

		<para>We don't try to guarantee completely robust and problem free
		behavior in cases where the caller or system isn't behaving. We
		consider these to be outside of our control:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Broken input from callers. We use preconditions
			to check input and immediately return. We don't try to provide
			error codes for all the various ways callers can screw
			around.</para></listitem>

			<listitem>
			<para>Out of memory. It is pretty much impossible to handle out
			of memory errors correctly. Handling them alongside other errors
			is naive and broken. We don't try to guarantee library state
			(such as locks or memory leaks) when memory allocation fails.</para>
			<para>We do check the results from all memory allocations, but
			treat them as unexpected conditions. As a nod to the behavior
			of callers of this library, we don't abort on memory allocation
			failures. We use preconditions with somewhat sane results.</para>
			<para>Exception: when reading files or allocating potentially
			unbounded amounts of memory, we should respond robustly to memory
			allocation failures.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>These unexpected conditions indicate a bug either in adcli or
		in the system. All bets are off once this occurs.</para>

		<para>Use the <literal>return_val_xxx()</literal> precondition macros to
		check for unexpected conditions.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="devel-testing">
		<title>Testing and Code Coverage</title>

		<para>Low level input parsers and such code should have unit tests
		excercizing it. Use the <literal>make check</literal> command to run all
		the tests. If you run it from a subdirectory only the tests in that
		directory will be run.</para>

		<para>To check for memory errors or memory leaks, run <literal>make memcheck</literal>
		or <literal>make leakcheck</literal> respectively. This requires valgrind
		be installed.</para>

		<para>Build adcli with the <option>--enable-coverage</option> configure
		option to build code coverage support.</para>

		<para>Once you've done that you can either use <literal>make coverage</literal>
		to build code coverage information. Alternatively (and this is usually
		easier) you can use
		<ulink url="http://stef.thewalter.net/2012/12/git-coverage-useful-code-coverage.html">
			<literal>git coverage</literal></ulink> to easily check whether
		you've tested the lines changed by a patch.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="devel-debugging">
		<title>Debugging Tips</title>

		<para>Unexpected conditions will produce critical warnings by adcli.
		These are often failed internal preconditions, and usually indicate a
		bug either in adcli or the software calling it.</para>

		<para>You can use the environment variable <literal>ADCLI_STRICT=yes</literal>
		to make adcli do an <literal>abort()</literal> (and core dump depending on
		your configuration) when a critical warning occurs.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
